Hello! Welcome to the world of Hangul, the easiest and most scientific alphabet in the world.
안녕하세요! 세상에서 가장 쉽고 과학적인 문자, 한글의 세계에 오신 것을 환영합니다.
In the early Joseon Dynasty, commoners who could not read faced many social disadvantages.
조선 초기, 글을 읽지 못하는 백성들은 많은 사회적 불이익을 겪었습니다.
Chinese characters were too complex to learn, making it impossible for ordinary people to gain knowledge.
중국의 한자는 배우기 너무 복잡해 일반 백성들이 지식을 쌓기 불가능했죠.
King Sejong, who pitied the suffering of his people, sought to create an easy, native writing system.
백성들의 고통을 가엾이 여긴 세종대왕은 쉬운 고유 문자를 창제하려 했습니다.
Despite opposition from the ruling class who defended Chinese characters, Sejong continued his work in secret.
한자를 옹호하는 지배층의 반대에도 불구하고 세종은 비밀리에 작업을 계속했죠.
Finally, in 1446, Hunminjeongeum, meaning 'the proper sounds for instructing the people', was promulgated.
마침내 1446년, 백성을 가르치는 바른 소리, '훈민정음'이 세상에 반포됩니다.
It embodies Sejong's love for the people, believing that writing should be easily used by everyone.
글이란 마땅히 모두가 편리하게 써야 한다는 세종의 애민 정신이 깃들어 있습니다.
Hangul is not just a phonetic alphabet; it is a featural alphabet where letter shapes reflect phonetic properties.
한글은 단순히 소리를 적는 표음문자를 넘어 모양에 소리 성질을 담은 자질 문자입니다.
A wise man can learn it in a morning, and even a simple man can learn it in ten days.
지혜로운 자는 아침에, 어리석은 자도 열흘이면 다 깨칠 정도로 배움이 쉽습니다.
Today, leading linguists worldwide praise Hangul as the most sophisticated writing system.
오늘날 세계 유수의 언어학자들은 한글을 가장 정교한 글자로 극찬하고 있죠.
Hangul's consonants mimic the actual shape of the vocal organs when producing sound.
한글의 자음은 소리를 낼 때 발음 기관이 움직이는 형태를 고스란히 본떴습니다.
The consonant 'G [k/g]' represents the root of the tongue blocking the throat.
자음 ㄱ은 혀뿌리가 목구멍을 막는 형태에서 따온 모양입니다.
The consonant 'N' depicts the tip of the tongue touching the upper gums.
자음 ㄴ은 혀끝이 윗잇몸에 가볍게 닿아 스치는 혀의 모습을 담았습니다.
The consonant 'M' is the outline of the lips meeting to open and close sounds.
자음 ㅁ은 네모난 입술이 서로 만나 소리를 닫고 여는 입의 입술 윤곽입니다.
The consonant 'S' represents the sharp shape of teeth where air friction is created.
자음 ㅅ은 공기를 마찰시키는 단단한 치아, 즉 이의 뾰족한 모양입니다.
The consonant 'NG' mimics the circular cross-section of the open throat.
자음 ㅇ은 열려 있는 둥근 목구멍의 단면을 고스란히 형상화한 것입니다.
Let's look at the structure of the 'G' sound when the tongue pulls back, narrowing the throat.
혀를 뒤로 당겨 목구멍을 좁힐 때 느껴지는 ㄱ소리의 발음 구조를 보시죠.
Feel the blockage of air as the tongue tip taps the upper gums when making the 'N' sound.
ㄴ소리를 낼 때 혀끝이 윗잇몸을 튕기며 내는 공기의 차단을 느껴보세요.
The comfortable bilabial movement of the 'M' sound, where lips close to gather sound and then release.
입술이 닫혀 소리가 모였다가 터지는 ㅁ소리의 편안한 양순음 움직임.
The alveolar fricative 'S' sound, where the tongue tip rests slightly behind the lower teeth as air escapes.
ㅅ소리가 새어 나올 때 혀끝이 아랫니 안쪽에 살짝 머무는 치경 마찰음.
This is the 'principle of stroke addition', adding lines to base shapes as sounds become stronger.
기본 다섯 글자에서 소리가 강해질 때 획을 더해가는 '가획의 원리'입니다.
Adding a stroke to 'ㄱ' makes 'ㅋ', visually representing a stronger burst of air.
ㄱ에 가획하여 ㅋ이 되며, 거센 공기의 뿜어냄이 시각적으로 더해집니다.
Adding a stroke to 'ㄴ' makes 'ㄷ', and adding another makes 'ㅌ'.
ㄴ에 획을 더해 ㄷ이 되고, 다시 한 번 획을 추가해 ㅌ이 탄생합니다.
Extending strokes on 'ㅁ' creates 'ㅂ', and adding more horizontal strokes completes 'ㅍ'.
ㅁ에 획을 세워 ㅂ을 만들고, 위아래 획을 더 확장해 ㅍ을 완성합니다.
Adding a top stroke to 'ㅅ' creates 'ㅈ', and another makes the aspirated 'ㅊ'.
ㅅ에 획을 얹어 ㅈ을 만들고, 다시 획을 얹어 거센소리 ㅊ으로 나아갑니다.
Adding strokes to 'ㅇ' forms 'ㅎ', representing strong breath passing through the throat.
ㅇ에 획을 얹어 ㅎ을 만들어, 거센 숨소리가 목구멍을 통과함을 나타냅니다.
Writing two identical letters side-by-side forms a tense, double consonant (Tense Sound).
글자를 나란히 두 개 겹쳐 쓰면, 더 단단하고 팽팽한 경음(쌍자음)이 됩니다.
ㄲ, ㄸ, ㅃ, ㅆ, and ㅉ are called double consonants, expressing tension in the larynx.
ㄲ, ㄸ, ㅃ, ㅆ, ㅉ을 각각 쌍자음이라 부르며, 후두의 긴장을 표현하죠.
Instead of adding regular strokes, the flowing liquid 'ㄹ' is created by curling the tongue.
설소리 ㄴ에 가획하지 않고, 혀를 굴려 흘려내는 특수 자음 ㄹ이 만들어집니다.
Thus, Hangul establishes a complete system of 19 consonants derived from the 5 base shapes.
이렇게 한글은 기본 5자에서 파생된 총 19개의 완벽한 자음 체계를 갖춥니다.
Vowels are structured differently, combining the three core cosmic elements: Sky, Earth, and Human.
모음은 자음과 완전히 다르게, 우주의 세 기본 요소인 천지인을 결합해 짭니다.
First is the round dot representing the sky, called 'Araea' (•).
첫째는 둥근 하늘의 모양을 상형한 하늘 '아래아'의 둥근 점입니다.
Second is the horizontal line representing the flat earth, 'EU' (ㅡ).
둘째는 평평하게 펼쳐진 대지의 모양을 본뜬 땅 '으'의 가로선입니다.
Third is the vertical line representing a standing human, 'I' (ㅣ).
셋째는 하늘과 땅 사이에 서서 존재하는 사람 '이'의 세로선입니다.
When Sky, Human, and Earth meet and combine, the basic vowels of Hangul are born.
하늘과 사람, 그리고 땅이 한데 만나 섞이며 한글의 기본 모음이 태어납니다.
If the sky (•) rises to the right of the human (ㅣ), it is 'A [a]'; to the left, it is 'EO [ʌ]'.
세로선 오른쪽에 하늘(•)이 뜨면 ㅏ, 왼쪽에 해가 지면 ㅓ가 됩니다.
If the sky rises above the earth (ㅡ), it is 'O [o]'; below the earth, it is 'U [u]'.
가로선 위로 하늘이 뜨면 ㅗ, 가로선 아래로 하늘이 숨으면 ㅜ가 됩니다.
The vowels 'ㅏ' and 'ㅗ', stretching outward and upward, are bright 'Yang' vowels.
해의 기운이 위와 밖으로 뻗어나가는 ㅏ, ㅗ는 밝고 긍정적인 양의 모음입니다.
The vowels 'ㅓ' and 'ㅜ', drawing inward and downward, are deep, calm 'Yin' vowels.
해의 기운이 안과 아래로 깃드는 ㅓ, ㅜ는 어둡고 차분한 음의 모음입니다.
Sky, Earth, and Human harmonize to complete the four base pillars of Hangul vowels.
하늘, 땅, 사람이 조화를 이루어 한글 모음의 기본 네 기둥을 완성합니다.
Adding the sky element twice creates y-glide diphthongs.
하늘의 기운(•)을 두 번씩 더 결합하면, y계열의 이중모음이 탄생합니다.
Adding it twice yields YA, YEO, YO, and YU, enriching the vowel spectrum.
해를 두 번 얹어 야, 여, 요, 유가 되어 소리가 한 층 다채로워집니다.
The vertical vowel 'I' merges with other vowels to create compound vowels.
모음 ㅣ와 다른 모음들이 한데 결합하여 새로운 합성 모음을 만듭니다.
ㅏ and ㅣ form 'AE', while ㅓ and ㅣ form 'E'.
ㅏ와 ㅣ가 만나 ㅐ가 되고, ㅓ와 ㅣ가 만나 ㅔ가 되어 발음이 고정됩니다.
The diphthongs YA and YEO combine with 'I' to form 'YAE' and 'YE'.
이중모음 ㅑ와 ㅣ가 만나 얘, ㅕ와 ㅣ가 만나 예가 되는 정교한 합성.
Horizontal vowels (ㅗ, ㅜ) combine with vertical ones to make rounded diphthongs.
가로 모음 ㅗ, ㅜ와 세로 모음들이 만나 입술을 둥글려 소리 내는 복합 모음.
O and A make 'WA'; U and EO make 'WO', flowing into double articulation.
오와 아가 만나 와가 되고, 우와 어가 만나 워가 되어 이중 조음이 흐릅니다.
OE, WI, and even WAE and WE require rounding the lips and shifting the tongue.
외와 위, 그리고 왜와 웨까지 입술을 모으며 혀를 움직이는 모음들.
The seemingly complex combination of ㅡ and ㅣ, 'UI', is a harmonious single flow.
가장 복잡해 보이는 ㅡ와 ㅣ의 결합, 의는 한 획으로 이어지는 조화입니다.
Starting from just 3 base shapes, Hangul boasts a rich system of 21 vowels.
이렇게 기본 3자에서 출발한 한글은 총 21개의 풍부한 모음 체계를 자랑합니다.
Let's learn the subtle differences in air pressure and vocal cord tension among plain, aspirated, and tense sounds.
평음, 격음, 경음의 미세한 공기 압력과 성대 긴장의 차이를 배워봅시다.
'G' is a relaxed plain sound, releasing air very softly and lightly.
ㄱ은 숨을 아주 부드럽고 가볍게 내보내며 내는 가장 편안한 소리입니다.
'K' is an aspirated sound, forcefully expelling air from deep within.
ㅋ은 가슴 깊은 곳에서 공기를 강하게 뿜어내며 뱉는 거센 소리입니다.
'KK' is a tense sound, compressing the vocal cords with almost no escaping air.
ㄲ은 공기를 내보내지 않고, 성대를 꽉 조였다가 터뜨리는 단단한 소리입니다.
You can feel the difference between plain 'G' and aspirated 'K' by putting your hand in front of your mouth.
평음 ㄱ과 격음 ㅋ의 차이는 손바닥을 입에 대고 바람을 느껴보면 쉽습니다.
The contrast between plain 'G' and tense 'KK' is like the 'K' in 'key' versus 'sky'.
평음 ㄱ과 경음 ㄲ은 영어의 key와 sky의 k소리 차이와 같습니다.
Hold a thin sheet of paper; it should bend back dramatically only when you pronounce 'K'.
입 앞에 얇은 종이를 두고 ㅋ을 할 때만 종이가 강하게 흔들려야 합니다.
When making the tense 'KK', pitch the following vowel higher and sharper.
경음 ㄲ을 낼 때는 첫 모음의 톤을 높은 음으로 강하게 질러 발음하세요.
Tense and aspirated sounds should feel crisp, with a distinct staccato separation.
경음과 격음은 소리를 낼 때 확실하게 맺고 끊는 staccato 느낌을 살립니다.
Solidify the 3-step difference of G/K/KK, D/T/TT, and B/P/PP in your mind.
ㄱ/ㅋ/ㄲ, ㄷ/ㅌ/ㄸ, ㅂ/ㅍ/ㅃ의 3단계 소리 차이를 완전히 머리로 정돈합니다.
Here is the precise articulation mechanism for the vowels that foreigners find hardest.
외국인이 가장 어려워하는 대표적인 모음들의 정밀 조음 메커니즘.
To pronounce 'EU [ɯ]', stretch your lips wide to the sides as if smiling.
으를 발음할 때는 입술을 양옆으로 길게 찢어 미소를 지으며 발음해야 합니다.
Keep the lips flat and unrounded, raising only the back of your tongue.
입술을 둥글게 오므리지 않고 납작하게 둔 채, 혀 뒷부분만 올려주세요.
To pronounce 'EO [ʌ]', drop your jaw low while keeping your lips relaxed and flat.
어를 발음할 때는 턱을 아래로 크게 벌리고, 입술은 둥글리지 않고 편안히 둡니다.
To pronounce 'O [o]', round your lips into a small, tight circle as if holding a straw.
오를 발음할 때는 빨대를 문 것처럼 입술을 아주 작고 둥글게 모아야 합니다.
Compare the wide jaw of 'EO' versus the tight circular lips of 'O'.
턱을 벌려 넓게 내는 어, 입술을 오므려 좁게 내는 오의 확연한 구강 차이.
For 'U [u]', purse your lips even tighter than 'O' and project them forward.
우는 입술을 오보다 더 둥글고 팽팽하게 모아서 앞으로 쭉 내밀어 줍니다.
Spot the difference: the tiny, tense circle of 'U' versus the medium circle of 'O'.
입을 아주 작고 강하게 오므리는 우, 그리고 중간 크기 모음 오의 차이.
Check in a mirror to make sure your lips do not round when saying 'EO' and 'EU'.
거울을 보고 ㅓ와 으를 발음할 때 입술이 동그랗게 변하지 않는지 꼭 체크하세요.
Fully master the combination of tongue height and lip rounding for EU, EO, O, and U.
으, 어, 오, 우의 혀의 높이와 입술 모양의 조화를 완벽하게 내 것으로 만듭니다.
Instead of aligning letters side-by-side, Hangul groups them into syllable blocks.
한글은 자모를 옆으로 늘어놓지 않고 하나의 음절 블록 안에 모아씁니다.
If the vowel has a vertical stroke (ㅣ), it sits to the right of the consonant.
모음의 획이 수직(ㅣ)으로 서 있으면, 자음의 오른쪽에 나란히 붙입니다.
If the vowel has a horizontal stroke (ㅡ), it sits directly under the consonant.
모음의 획이 수평(ㅡ)으로 누워 있으면, 자음의 아래쪽에 얹어 씁니다.
Vowels with both horizontal and vertical strokes wrap around the right and bottom of the consonant.
가로와 세로 획이 모두 있는 모음은 자음의 오른쪽과 아래쪽을 모두 감쌉니다.
The final consonant placed at the very bottom of a syllable is called 'Batchim'.
음절의 맨 밑바닥에 마지막으로 붙여 쓰는 자음을 '받침(종성)'이라 합니다.
A final consonant joins below, completing a 3-layered syllable like 'GANG'.
자음과 모음 결합 아래에 받침 자음이 조립되어 삼층 구조의 강을 완성하죠.
Though many consonants can be written as Batchim, they are pronounced as only 7 sounds.
받침으로 쓰이는 자음은 많지만, 실제 발음은 오직 7개의 소리로 제한됩니다.
The final consonants ㅅ, ㅆ, ㅈ, ㅊ, ㄷ, ㅌ, and ㅎ all collapse into the representative 'D [t]' sound.
ㅅ, ㅆ, ㅈ, ㅊ, ㄷ, ㅌ, ㅎ 받침은 모두 바닥에서 대표음 ㄷ[t]로 발음됩니다.
Batchim sounds are unreleased, stopping air flow abruptly inside the mouth.
받침소리는 공기를 밖으로 터뜨리지 않고 입안에서 딱 멈추는 불파음입니다.
Sometimes double/complex Batchims appear, where only one consonant is voiced.
때로는 두 자음이 겹쳐 쓰이는 겹받침이 오며, 원칙에 따라 하나만 소리 납니다.
When a Batchim is followed by an empty 'ㅇ', the sound links over to the next syllable.
받침 뒤에 빈자리인 ㅇ이 오면, 받침소리가 뒷자리로 넘어가 연음됩니다.
'Babeul' is read as [ba-beul], and 'kkochi' as [kko-chi], flowing naturally.
밥을은 [바블]로, 꽃이는 [꼬치]로 소리가 흐르듯 자연스럽게 이어지죠.
When G, D, B meet N or M, they shift to soft nasal sounds: NG, N, M.
ㄱ, ㄷ, ㅂ 뒤에 ㄴ, ㅁ이 오면, 소리가 부드러운 비음 ㅇ, ㄴ, ㅁ으로 변합니다.
In 'Gamsahamnida', 'hap-ni' is pronounced as [ham-ni], making it smoother to say.
감사합니다의 합니는 함니로 발음되어 훨씬 발음하기 부드러워집니다.
When a final D or T meets the vowel 'I', it palatalizes into J or CH.
ㄷ, ㅌ 받침 뒤에 모음 ㅣ가 오면 ㅈ, ㅊ으로 입을 가볍게 치켜 올립니다.
Reading 'gudi' as [guji] and 'gati' as [gachi] is similar to 'would you' in English.
굳이는 [구지]로, 같이는 [가치]로 발음되는 현상은 영어의 would you와 유사하죠.
When N and L meet, both assimilate into a smooth, liquid double 'L' sound.
ㄴ과 ㄹ이 서로 이웃해 만나면, 두 소리 모두 매끄러운 ㄹㄹ소리로 바뀝니다.
While English moves to stress-based rhythm, Korean flows flatly based on syllable blocks.
영어가 강세에 따라 움직인다면, 한국어는 음절박자로 평평하게 흐릅니다.
Rather than chopping words apart, let them glide, riding the natural sound changes.
단어들을 뚝뚝 끊어 읽지 말고, 연음과 발음 변화를 타며 흘리듯 읽으세요.
Congratulations on mastering Hangul! Join our new learning journey with a subscribe and like!
한글을 마스터한 여러분을 축하합니다! 새로운 한글의 여정을 구독과 좋아요로!